cira.ca 2009-04-10

# 

                    CIRA POLICIES, RULES AND PROCEDURES
                           CIRA Privacy Policy (Version 1.6)
We, the Canadian Internet Registration Authority (CIRA) are dedicated to maintaining
both a high standard of privacy and a high standard of data protection in all of our
activities. We must balance that respect for the privacy rights of our customers,
employees and contractors with our public responsibilities in the administration of the
Canadian country code top-level domain (dot-ca). We also must consider the
responsibility of ensuring that thorough security measures are in effect. This may involve
verifying and testing assertions, practices, and the conduct of individuals and
organizations and may have an impact on, or involve the use of, personal information.
This privacy policy (the “Policy”), in a manner consistent with the principles set out in
the Personal Information Protection and Electronic Documents Act (PIPEDA), reflects
CIRA’s interpretation of these responsibilities. We welcome your comments and
suggestions. The Policy is divided into 10 sections.
Capitalized terms used in this Policy that are not defined in this Policy have the meanings
specified in By-Law No. 1 of CIRA.
INDEX
    !   What is Personal Information
    !   Accountability
    !   Purpose
    !   Consent
    !   Collection and Use
    !   Disclosure
    !   Accuracy and Retention
    !   Safeguards
    !   Access to Information
    !   Feedback and Complaints
1.      What is Personal Information (back to index)
Personal information is information about an identifiable individual. This, however, does
not include:
(a)     the name;
(b)     title;
(c)     business address; and
(d)     business telephone number,

of an employee of an organization.
In addition, information which is anonymous, i.e., where the identifying data fields are
removed, is also not considered personal information.
2.      Accountability (back to index)
You may contact the Chief Privacy Officer at privacy@cira.ca, or by writing to:
Chief Privacy Officer
Canadian Internet Registration Authority
350 Sparks Street
Suite 306
Ottawa, Ontario
K1R 7S8
Fax: 613-237-0534
All contractors and other third parties with whom we have a contractual arrangement and
with whom we share personal data are contractually obligated to ensure that their
practices meet our standards and are fully compliant with applicable privacy legislation.
3.      Purpose (back to index)
CIRA operates and administers the dot-ca Internet domain name Registry and any
ancillary matters related and/or linked thereto. This entails the management of personal
data. Historically, much of the information about Registrants that has been collected by
domain name registries, whether the Registrants are natural or legal persons, has been
made available over the Internet through the WHOIS database and we too offer certain
Registrant information via the WHOIS in accordance with this policy.
We require the information for the reasonable purposes of the operation of the Registry
and the implementation, execution, and enforcement of the applicable Registry policies,
rules, and procedures. We, in essence, act as the repository for the information. This
permits greater flexibility and transferability of domain names from Registrant to
Registrant or Registrar to Registrar. In addition, it permits us to fulfill our overall role
and mandate as an independent and neutral third party, to ensure public policy objectives
in the operation of the Registry, such as fair competition, management of a scarce
resource, reasonable access for all, and protection of privacy and personal information. In
addition, personal information about Registrants may be collected and used for the
following additional purposes:
    !   To register a dot-ca domain name;
    !   To manage a dot-ca Domain Name Registration;
    !   To enable others to check a registration;
                                                                                           2

    !   To maintain membership records;
    !   To contact Registrants about CIRA member issues, domain name registration
        issues, and in order to facilitate the resolution of any kind of dispute (be it via the
        CIRA Dispute Resolution Process or any other judicial process);
    !   To contact Registrants in order to forward to them correspondence sent to a
        Registrant via CIRA by a third party;
    !   To ensure good customer service, in the event a Registrant requires support or
        makes inquiries;
    !   To identify the individual(s) to law enforcement agencies, competent courts, and
        other competent judicial bodies under appropriate legal circumstances; and
    !   To enable us to manage the dot-ca Registry in accordance with our by-laws.
Personal information may be gathered from the public and used in the following
situations:
    !   If an individual visits our website, the web server logs IP addresses and associated
        information relating to the requests made;
    !   If an individual initiates a CIRA process, then we may gather transactional
        information as part of the process;
    !   If an individual makes an inquiry or complaint, applies for a job, or visits the
        premises;
    !   If an individual responds to a survey or a call for public comment;
    !   If an individual registers for a CIRA event, activity, or contest; and
    !   If an individual corresponds with us in writing.
Finally, regardless as to how and from whom we collected information, we will not sell
or provide your personal information to any organization for any purpose other than in
compliance with the Policy.
4.      Consent (back to index)
We, pursuant to the Purpose, require the submission of personal information from any
individual who wishes to become a Registrant for the purpose of registration of domain
names. We have attempted to limit the information we collect to that which is necessary
for this purpose. Domain name registration is done online, and we seek the positive
affirmation of all Registrants:
                                                                                              3

    !   That they have read and understood this policy;
    !   That they understand that we require the information for the proper operation of
        the Registry; and
    !   That they agree to the collection, use and disclosure of their personal information
        as described herein.
Individuals may withdraw consent for the further use of their information at any time, by
contacting our Chief Privacy Officer. However, if the information in question is that
which must be collected in order to register a domain name, withdrawing consent will
lead to the cancellation of the Domain Name Registration.
5.      Collection and Use (back to index)
This section lists the data elements that are most commonly collected and used in
connection with a Domain Name Registration:
(a)     With regard to all Registrants:
    !   each Domain Name registered in the name of the Registrant and each domain
        number as assigned by CIRA;
    !   the Registrant’s name and the Authorized Representative’s (as defined in section
        1.2(e) of the Registrant Agreement) name and the Registrant’s and, if applicable,
        the Authorized Representative’s postal address, email address(es), telephone
        number(s), and, where available, fax number(s), and the Registrant’s Registrant
        number as assigned by CIRA;
    !   the description field which the Registrant or the Registrant’s Registrar filled out
        during the registration process describing the Registrant or the Registrant’s
        business;
    !   the Registrant’s “Pretty Good Privacy” (“PGP”) public encryption key, if the
        Registrant elects to use PGP encrypted email when communicating with CIRA;
    !   the name(s), postal address(es), email address(es), telephone number(s) and where
        available, the fax number(s) of the Administrative Contacts for each Domain
        Name Registration;
    !   the name(s), postal address(es), email address(es), telephone number(s) and where
        available, the fax number(s) of the Technical Contacts for each Domain Name
        Registration;
                                                                                          4

    ! the Internet Protocol address of the primary name server and secondary name
      server and, if applicable, the tertiary, quaternary, quinary, and senary name
      servers for each Domain Name Registration;
    ! the corresponding names of those name servers;
    ! the registration date and the last changed date of each Domain Name Registration;
    ! whether the Domain Name Registration has been suspended or is in the process of
      being transferred;
    ! the expiration date of each Domain Name Registration of the Registrant;
    ! we may contact Registrants to inform them of Domain Name Registration issues,
      conferences, elections, user feedback and market intelligence, or other matters
      related to their Domain Name Registration;
    ! the IP address, time, date, and the type of transaction the person was involved in;
    ! any historical information about the transactions in regard to a domain name
      and/or a Registrant;
    ! any response to a CIRA dispute resolution process complaint;
    ! information to authenticate the identity and existence of a Registrant as may be
      required pursuant to the Manual Change of Administrative Contact Policies,
      Rules and Procedures;
    ! information to authenticate the existence and identity of Members and
      Membership Representatives as may be required pursuant to the Policy on
      Membership; and
    ! information collected for verification purposes in accordance with our Registry
      policies, rules and procedures.
(b)   With regard to Registrants who are not individuals and who are, or apply to
      become, Members of CIRA as defined in By-law No. 1 (“Members”):
    ! Information to authenticate the existence and identity of Registrants and
      Membership Representatives; and
    ! the name(s), postal address(es), email address(es), telephone number(s), job title,
      and, where available, the fax number(s) of the Membership Representative;
(c)   With regard to Registrants who are Members of CIRA:
                                                                                          5

    ! CIRA uses information collected for membership purposes (“Membership
      Information”) as may be required by law and/or to authenticate Members and to
      conduct all affairs of CIRA that involve Members.
(d)   With regard to Registrants or potential Registrants who have a dispute that they
      wish to settle:
    ! The name(s), postal address(es), email address(es), telephone number(s) and the
      fax number(s) of the Complainant and any representative authorized to act for the
      Complainant in the CIRA dispute resolution process; and
    ! The complaint and any supporting material thereof.
(e)   With regard to visitors to our website:
    ! We may use session cookies to ensure a smooth and convenient site visit;
    ! The previous page visited prior to accessing our web page is automatically logged
      by the servers; and
    ! For a detailed discussion of cookies and web server logs, you may wish to consult
      www.epic.org, or www.privcom.gc.ca.
(f)   With regard to individuals who contact us:
    ! To apply for a job, we send the resume or letter to the human resource department
      which will keep it for one year;
    ! By telephone, we may record the call for the purposes of ensuring quality control.
      Individuals are offered the opportunity to opt-out;
    ! By writing, we may keep copies of the correspondence for business purposes such
      as dealing with our contractors and partners, providing good customer service,
      and if applicable, statutory compliance;
    ! If an individual arrives at our offices in person, their entry to and exit from the
      premises may be captured by security cameras and retained on video tape; and
    ! Unless other retention periods apply, we send personal correspondence to the
      appropriate responsibility centre which we will keep for one year.
(g)   With regard to contractors and partners:
    ! All contractors and partners are contractually bound to abide by all applicable
      privacy legislation. If they work onsite, they will have security control badges and
      are in many respects treated like staff;
                                                                                         6

    !    Information collected for employment and payment may include name, address,
         phone number, social insurance number, bank account information, business and
         GST registration numbers, references, etc.;
    !    We share all of our information with our auditors, who are bound to CIRA by
         contract and by professional rules to maintain confidentiality and return all
         documents to us; and
    !    We have the right to audit any of our Registrars. In the event of an investigation
         of a Registrar for fraud, criminal activity, breach of contract, or just quality
         assurance, we may enter the premises and acquire personal information of both
         Registrants and staff of the Registrar. This right is agreed to by contract.
6.       Disclosures and Transfers (back to index)
CIRA operates and administers the dot-ca Internet domain name Registry and any
ancillary matters related and/or linked thereto. We do not use information for secondary
marketing purposes, and do not share or disclose the information to other parties unless
specifically stated in this policy. We do disclose information which may include personal
information in the following circumstances.
CIRA may hire reputable third party organizations to carry out the activities involved in
operating the .ca domain name Registry on CIRA’s behalf. Before transferring any
information to any third party service provider, CIRA enters into an agreement with the
service provider pursuant to which it is required to use the information solely for the
purpose of providing the service and to maintain security and privacy measures at least as
stringent as those of CIRA.
CIRA will also provide, to a person who, in accordance with our “Registration
Information Access Rules and Procedures” (at http://www.cira.ca/en/cat_Registrar.html)
requests in writing, a list of the dot-ca domain names registered in the name of a
Registrant or registered in the name of the same Registrant as a domain name identified
by the requester even if the identity of the Registrant is unknown. This is done to
facilitate bona fide rights holders to determine infringements of intellectual property
rights.
We will disclose personal information, other than via the WHOIS, as stated below, and
the “Registration Information Access Rules and Procedures”, as explained above, only:
(a)      in the event that a law enforcement agency, court of competent jurisdiction,
         tribunal, judicial board, administrative body, judicial commission, or any other
         judicial body of competent jurisdiction compels the disclosure of personal
         information by way of a legally binding order, ruling, decision, subpoena,
         warrant, or judgment;
                                                                                          7

(b)       in a manner consistent with the principles set out in the Personal Information
         Protection and Electronic Documents Act S.C. 2000, c. 5; or
(c)      if the domain name is subject to a proceeding under the CIRA Dispute Resolution
         Policy, to the relevant Dispute Resolution Provider.
We shall, unless prohibited by law, not less than thirty (30) and not more than sixty (60)
days after disclosure of the personal information, use reasonable efforts to send an email
to the Administrative Contact e-mail address of the Registrant for the relevant Domain
Name Registration(s) indicating:
(a)      what parts of the information we disclosed; and
(b)      to whom we disclosed it.
6.1      WHOIS
As part of our administration of the dot-ca registry, we operate an electronic look-up
service called the WHOIS. The WHOIS is designed to provide limited information to site
visitors about assigned dot-ca domain names for the following purposes: (a) to allow
network administrators to find and fix system problems and to generally maintain the
stability of the Internet; (b) to help combat inappropriate uses of the Internet such as
spam or fraud; (c) to facilitate the identification of instances of trademark infringement;
and (d) generally to enhance accountability of dot-ca domain name Registrants. More
generally, the WHOIS permits us to fulfill our primary role and mandate as an
independent and neutral top level domain name registry and to ensure the attainment of
public policy objectives in the operation of the dot-ca registry, including the facilitation
of fair competition, the management of a scarce resource, the maintenance of reasonable
access for all and the protection of privacy and personal information.
Following a substantive review conducted during 2003-2004, we amended our
operational and policy approaches to WHOIS in order to achieve a number of policy
objectives, including the enhancement of Registrant privacy. In particular, we imposed
significant new limits upon the disclosure of Registrant data via WHOIS and upon the
entitlements of third parties to use information acquired via WHOIS. Our rules governing
WHOIS are set forth below.
6.1.1    Disclosure of Information Concerning Domains Registered to Individual
         Registrants.
The following information concerning dot-ca domains registered to Registrants who are
individuals and who are Canadian citizens, permanent residents, legal representatives or
aboriginal persons as they are all defined in the General Registration Rules (collectively
referred to as “Individual Registrants” for the purposes of this Part 6 of this Policy) shall
be made accessible to interested third parties through the WHOIS:
                                                                                           8

(a)     domain name(s);
(b)     Individual Registrant’s Registrar’s name;
(c)     Individual Registrant’s Registrar’s number assigned by us;
(d)     the expiration date of each Domain Name Registration of an Individual
        Registrant;
(e)     the registration date of each Domain Name Registration;
(f)     the last changed date of each Domain Name Registration;
(g)     whether the Domain Name Registration has been suspended or is in the process of
        being transferred;
(h)     the Internet Protocol address of the primary name server and secondary name
        server(s) and, if applicable, the tertiary, quaternary, quinary, and senary name
        servers for each Domain Name Registration; and
(i)     the corresponding names of those name servers.
6.1.2 Disclosure of Additional Information to Registrars who are not the
        Registrant’s Registrar of Record.
For the reasonable purposes of the operation of the Registry as described in Part 3 above
and, more specifically, to facilitate Registrar to Registrar transfers, merge transactions,
Registrant to Registrant transfers, the addition of new Domain Name Registrations to an
existing Individual Registrant profile and any other transaction for which the relevant
Registrar who is not the Registrant’s Registrar of Record reasonably requires additional
Registration Information, as determined by us at our reasonable discretion, the following
information will be disclosed by us to the relevant Registrar who is not the Individual
Registrant’s Registrar of Record:
(a)     Individual Registrant name;
(b)     the description field which the Individual Registrant or the Individual Registrant’s
        Registrar filled out during the registration process describing the Individual
        Registrant or the Individual Registrant’s business;
(c)     Individual Registrant number as assigned by us;
(d)     Domain Name number as assigned by us;
(e)     the Individual Registrant’s postal address, email address, telephone number and
        where available, the fax number for each Domain Name Registration;
                                                                                           9

(f)     the name, postal address, email address, telephone number and where available,
        the fax number of the Administrative Contacts for each Domain Name
        Registration;
(g)     the name, postal address, email address, telephone number and where available,
        the fax number of the Technical Contacts for each Domain Name Registration;
(h)     the name, postal address, email address, telephone number and where available,
        the fax number of the Authorized Representative for each Domain Name
        Registration;
(i)     the Registrant’s privacy settings; and
(j)     other information through systems other than the WHOIS as may be required to
        facilitate the operation of the Registry.
6.1.3   Consent to Disclose Additional Registration Information via the WHOIS.
An Individual Registrant may voluntarily opt to disclose via the WHOIS, and in
accordance with this section 6.1.3, more registration information than is provided for in
section 6.1.1, including:
(a)     Individual Registrant name;
(b)     the description field which the Individual Registrant or the Individual Registrant’s
        Registrar filled out during the registration process describing the Individual
        Registrant or the Individual Registrant’s business;
(c)     Individual Registrant number as assigned by us;
(d)     Domain Name number as assigned by us;
(e)     the Individual Registrant’s postal address, email address, telephone number and,
        where available, the fax number for each Domain Name Registration;
(f)     the name, postal address, email address, telephone number and, where available,
        the fax number of the Administrative Contacts for each Domain Name
        Registration;
(g)     the name, postal address, email address, telephone number and, where available,
        the fax number of the Technical Contacts for each Domain Name Registration;
        and
(h)     the name, postal address, email address, telephone number and, where available,
        the fax number of the Authorized Representative for each Domain Name
        Registration.
                                                                                         10

Our ability to control the uses made of information disclosed via the WHOIS is very
limited, regardless of whether that information becomes subject to domestic or foreign
privacy laws when acquired by a third party. Nonetheless, we have sought to impose
limitations, through section 6.1.5 of this Policy, upon third party uses of WHOIS data.
6.1.4 Registrants other than Individual Registrants as Defined Above.
In the normal course, all registration information collected by us from Registrants of dot-
ca domain names who are not individuals will be made accessible to the public through
the WHOIS. However, Registrants of dot-ca domain names who are not individuals may
request, in writing via email, that the information described in section 6.1.2 not be
disclosed by us to the public via the WHOIS. We may, at our reasonable discretion,
permit such a request. If we accede to the request, information as set out in section 6.1.2
will only be disclosed thereafter in accordance with the terms for disclosure applicable to
Individual Registrants.
In the written request referred to above, the Registrant who is not an individual must
certify that it has a legitimate need to protect the privacy of its information, which need is
greater than that of other CIRA Registrants who are not individuals, because the nature of
that Registrant’s operations or activities is such that disclosure of its information via the
WHOIS would be likely to cause harm to individuals or to that Registrant. The Registrant
who is not an individual should provide a short confidential explanation to CIRA
explaining how it meets these criteria.
CIRA retains the discretion to determine in any case whether a Registrant who is not an
Individual meets the criteria and will be permitted to opt out of standard disclosure of
information in the WHOIS.
6.1.5 Use of WHOIS Service.
Any person may use the WHOIS service, provided it is for the following purposes only:
(a)     to query the availability of a domain name;
(b)     where permitted, to identify the holder of a domain name; and/or
(c)     where permitted, to obtain contact and/or other information concerning (i)
        Individual Registrants and/or Registrants who are not individuals and the domain
        names that they have registered; and (ii) Registrars, Administrative Contacts,
        Technical Contacts and/or Authorized Representatives.
Information acquired from the WHOIS shall not be used for any purposes other than
those referenced above. Purposes which are prohibited shall include, but are not limited
to, the carrying out of any activities which are unsolicited and can reasonably be viewed
as involving the harvesting of WHOIS addresses (electronic or otherwise) for the purpose
of transmitting by e-mail, telephone, facsimile, or regular mail any commercial
                                                                                           11

advertising; the performance of market research; solicitation activities; and/or or any
other purposes which may be reasonably viewed as intrusive to a reasonable domain
name holder. No user of the WHOIS is permitted to utilize automated and/or electronic
processes that send queries or data to the WHOIS, except as is reasonably necessary to
perform transactions related to domain names.
7.       Accuracy and Retention (back to index)
It is important that the information we obtain from Registrants is accurate. Information
that we will act on, (such as contact information, complaints, disputes, resumes, etc.)
must be accurate. If you think we have information about you that is not accurate, you are
encouraged to contact us at the address provided in Section 10 of this policy and indicate
the necessary changes. We may require that you follow certain procedures that are
utilized by us for the authentication and verification of your identity.
We retain information according to retention schedules, which depend on the purpose of
the information and any legal or contractual requirements with which we might need to
comply.
8.       Safeguards (back to index)
It is important that the information maintained by us on behalf of Registrants is accurate,
protected from interference by other parties, and treated in confidence by as few
personnel as necessary. We maintain state of the art firewall and antivirus protection on
our servers, train our staff, and hire only responsible and capable contractors to manage
our systems. If you detect any anomalies that might lead you to believe there has been a
security infraction or hacking of our system, we will be pleased to investigate. Please
contact security@cira.ca.
9.       Access to Information (back to index)
The intention of this policy is to answer your questions about our privacy policy and
practices. Should you be interested in more detailed information about our procedures
and practices, please contact our Chief Privacy Officer (CPO) at privacy@cira.ca.
Should you wish to access your own personal information, please write to our CPO at
privacy@cira.ca. Upon receipt of a request from you, our CPO will send you, by email,
mail, or facsimile, an “Access Request Form” or a “Correction Request Form” for you to
fill out. Provided we can, to our satisfaction, authenticate your identity and subject to
certain exceptions prescribed by law, you will be given reasonable access to your
personal information and/or you will be entitled to challenge the accuracy and
completeness of the information and have it appropriately amended. If you are interested
in correcting information, related to your Domain Name Registration, (after having
reviewed the information you obtained from us via this procedure), we will be pleased to
forward the request to your Registrar. The routine procedures for correcting registration
information will be followed, unless you have described to us extraordinary
circumstances that would warrant the use of a different procedure. In most cases, the
                                                                                        12

routine procedures are the most efficient procedures for correcting registration
information.
At the time of your request, we may need further information from you to verify your
identity, before we can provide you with the personal information we hold.
There may be instances when we will not be able to provide you with the personal
information that you request. For example, if the personal information:
    !   Contains references to other persons;
    !   Has already been destroyed due to legal requirements or because we no longer
        needed it for our purposes;
    !   Is subject to solicitor-client or litigation privilege; and/or
    !   Cannot be disclosed for other legal reasons.
If you are a Registrant, and if you wish to see the current information that others see in a
WHOIS search, you may do so by typing your dot-ca domain name in the WHOIS search
engine.
10.     Feedback and Complaints (back to index)
We take privacy seriously and consider that our treatment of personal information is part
of the service that we offer. We appreciate hearing any comments that you may have
about our policy, practices, and customer service. Please contact:
Chief Privacy Officer
Canadian Internet Registration Authority
350 Sparks Street
Suite 306
Ottawa, Ontario
K1R 7S8
privacy@cira.ca
                                                                                         13
